# **Hugo Alberto Ayala Solares**

#### **PhD Physics**

@ hgayala@psu.edu O github.com/havalaso **\** 218-235-9991

State College, PA, USA orcid.org/0000-0002-2084-5049

% https://hugoayala.netlify.com/

in www.linkedin.com/in/hgayalaso

# **SUMMARY OF QUALIFICATIONS**

Ph.D. physicist that is always trying to learn and apply new knowledge. My current focus is in observational astrophysics. I apply statistical tools and probability to find interesting events in the data. I also use optimization methods to find models that describe the data with frequentist and bayesian statistics. I perform simulations to characterize analyses. I manage and maintain a real-time system that receives and analyze large datasets. I have experience working with large collaborations as well as leading smaller groups within them.

# **TECHNICAL SKILLS**

Numpy, Matplotlib, Scipy, Pandas, TensorFlow, Astropy

C++

Bash Git

MySQL LaTex

**Data Structures and Algorithms** 

Optimization

**Machine Learning** 

Clustering, Classification

**Probability** 

Frequentist, Bayesian

**Statistical Analysis** 

Parameter estimation, regression

**Physics** 

# **BUSINESS AND SOCIAL SKILLS**

**Effective communicator** 

Presentation skills

Adaptable to different audiences

Led collaborative teams

**Process oriented** Fast learner

Strategic thinking

# WORK EXPERIENCE

#### PostDoctoral Researcher

Pennsylvania State University

May 2017 - Ongoing

- State College, PA, United States
- Builiding and maintaining the Astrophyliscal Multimessenger Observatory Network (AMON).
- Develop coincidence analyses between different datasets to find candidate astrophysical multimessenger sources.
  - Search for sources of gamma-ray and neutrino emission by using a multimessenger approach.
- Member of the High Altitude Water Cherenkov (HAWC) Observatory.
  - Study gamma-ray emission from large-scale structures with HAWC data. Calculating credible intervals on the amount of emission of these sources.
  - Extragalactic and Multimessenger/Multiwavelenght coordinator in HAWC.
- Associate Member of the IceCube Neutrino Observatory.
- Presented work in more than 10 conferences and collaboration meetings in the past 3 years.

#### Ph.D. Researcher

Michigan Technological University

**2011-2017** 

- ♦ Houghton,MI,United States
- Created and maintained laser calibration system of the HAWC detector.
- Developed optimization algorithms to reconstruct astrophysical events.
- Developed a statistical analysis to search for weak signal in high-level background

#### **Research Intern**

Photonics and Mathematical-Optics Group, ITESM

**Spring 2011** 

♥ Monterrey, N.L. Mexico

• Studied equations for spiral profiles of light after passing through birefringent objects.

### **EDUCATION**

#### Ph.D. in Physics focused on Astrophysics

Michigan Technological University

September 2011 - April 2017

♥ Houghton, MI, United States

Thesis title: Search for High-Energy Gamma Rays in the Northern Fermi Bubble Region with the HAWC Observatory

#### **B.Sc.** in Engineering Physics

Instituto Tecnológico y de Estudios Superiores de Monterrey

August 2006 - December 2010

♥ Monterrey, N.L., Mexico

## **LANGUAGES**

SpanishEnglishGermanNative LanguageFluentIntermediate

# LATEST PUBLICATIONS

### Journal Articles

- Ayala Solares, H.A. et al. (2021). "Multimessenger Gamma-Ray and Neutrino Coincidence Alerts using HAWC and IceCube sub-threshold Data". In: *ApJ* 906, p. 63. DOI: https://doi.org/10.3847/1538-4357/abcaa4.
- Solares, Hugo A. Ayala et al. (2020). "The Astrophysical Multimessenger Observatory Network (AMON): Performance and science program". In: Astroparticle Physics 114, pp. 68–76. ISSN: 0927-6505. DOI: https://doi.org/10.1016/j.astropartphys.2019.06.007. URL: http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0927650519301227.
- Ayala Solares, Hugo Alberto (2019). "AMON Multimessenger Alerts: Past and Future". In: *Galaxies* 7.1. ISSN: 2075-4434. DOI: 10.3390/galaxies7010019. URL: https://www.mdpi.com/2075-4434/7/1/19.
- Solares, H. A. Ayala et al. (2019). "A Search for Cosmic Neutrino and Gamma-Ray Emitting Transients in 7.3 yr of ANTARES and Fermi LAT Data". In: *The Astrophysical Journal* 886.2, p. 98. DOI: 10.3847/1538-4357/ab4a74. URL: https://doi.org/10.3847%2F1538-4357%2Fab4a74.

### **AWARDS**

- Funding from Swift Guest Investigator Program NASA Cycle 15
- Funding from Swift Guest Investigator Program NASA Cycle 16